A Guide to the Leonard Outhwaite Papers FA059
Rockefeller Archive Center
Leonard Outhwaite papers
1929-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Outhwaite, Leonard
Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial
FA059
5.81 Cubic Feet 14 boxes, 1 oversized folder
Arrangement note
The Leonard Outhwaite Collection is divided into four series:
Series 1 - Biographical Material
Series 2 - Projects
Series 3 - Research and Writing
Series 1034 - Photographs
Biographical/Historical note
Leonard Outhwaite, 1892-1979, worked as a consultant, an anthropologist, and an author.
Mr. Outhwaite was a staff member of the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial from 1923 to 1928 where one of his fields of interest was American race relations.
In the 1930s, Mr. Outhwaite served The Rockefeller Foundation as a consultant in anthropology. In this capacity he studied the development of the field of anthropology in American and foreign universities and produced a report, "Primitive Man in the Modern World." His consultancy with the Foundation also involved studying and preparing a report on the educational programs at art, science, and natural history museums. Following his service at the Foundation, Mr. Outhwaite served as a consultant to various museums and zoos and organized Outhwaite Exhibits, to design and construct museum, commercial, and World's Fair exhibitions.
Mr. Outhwaite also served the United States government immediately prior to, during, and after World War II. Among his posts were director of resettlement, Farm Security Administration; chief science analyst, Bureau of the Budget; director, Federal Board of Hospitalization. He also worked as a consultant for the Office of Production Management, Natural Resources Planning Board, and served as executive secretary to the Conference on Postwar Adjustment of Civilian and Military Personnel. He prepared a conference report that contributed to the Veterans Bill of Rights.
In 1948, Mr. Outhwaite, working for Laurance S. Rockefeller, prepared a report on population and population research.
He also served as research director of Nature Centers, Inc. As a consultant for the Institute of Public Administration, he prepared a study, "Museums and the Future," which was published in 1967.
Mr. Outhwaite held an interest in anthropology and exploration. In 1929-1930 he covered 14,000 miles of the Atlantic Ocean on an expedition aboard the yacht "Kinkajou," during which he visited Mt. Pele, Martinique.
Mr. Outhwaite was the author of several books, including "The Atlantic: The History of an Ocean" and "Unrolling the Map." He also prepared an unpublished manuscript, "Life and Times of the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial," an account based on his tenure as a staff member of that organization.
Related Archival Materials note
Additional material concerning Mr. Outhwaite appears in the archives of the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 3A 01
Conditions Governing Access
Open for researchd. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains biographical material, correspondence, articles, books, studies, and photographs pertaining to Leonard Outhwaite's various achievements and activities.
- Biographical Material, 1930-1978; 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The biographical material in Series 1 includes the transcript of an oral history interview given by Mr. Outhwaite in 1976.
  - Affiliations, 1957-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The Union Club; Yale University.
  - Government Service, 1941-1948, 1976, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oral History, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1930-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Work Histories, 1938-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Projects, 1929-1962; 2
  The papers in Series 2 deal with, among other topics, inventions on which Mr. Outhwaite worked and exhibits which he prepared.
  - Consulting, 1938-1962, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Exhibits - People in Time and Space, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Exhibits - World's Fairs, 1937-1938, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inventions - The Negative Balloon, 1961, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Inventions - Research Material, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Inventions - Televisions - Radio Corporation of America - Advanced Design Center, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Publicity - Nature Centers for Young America, Inc. - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Publicity - Nature Centers for Young America, Inc. - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Travel - Kinkajou - Clippings, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Research and Writing, 1930-1978; 3
  The material in Series 3 includes research notes, correspondence, and drafts relating to various fictional and non-fictional writings.
  - Articles - "Erewhon" - Samuel Butler Centennial, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Articles - "The Fabulous Fifties"; "The Great Illusion" (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Articles - "The Invasion of America", 1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Articles - "Masterpieces of Courage", 1931 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Articles - "The Universe in Your Pocket", undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Articles - "Vanishing Races", 1933 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Articles - "Yankee Doodle"; "You and the Captain" (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Books - Fiction - "High Lake" (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Books - Fiction - "Lightship", 1937 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Books - Fiction - "Night Club" - Parts I-II - Typescript (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Books - Fiction - "Night Club" - Parts I-II - Typescript (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Books - Fiction - "Ulysses" - Typescript (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Atlantic Circle" - Correspondence, 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Atlantic Circle" - Manuscript (Incomplete) (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Atlantic: History of an Ocean" - Correspondence and Editorial Comment, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Atlantic: History of an Ocean" - Maps, Notes, Outlines, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Atlantic: History of an Ocean" - Typescripts - Part I, Chapter 1 through Part II, Chapter 26 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Atlantic: History of an Ocean" - Typescripts - Part I, Chapter 1 through Part II, Chapter 26 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Atlantic: History of an Ocean" - Typescripts - Part I, Chapter 1 through Part II, Chapter 26 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Atlantic: History of an Ocean" - Typescripts - Part I, Chapter 1 through Part II, Chapter 26 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Explorer's Club History of World Exploration" - Correspondence and Outlines, 1942-1965 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Notes and Outlines, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Research Files (Agriculture - Butter) (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Research Files (Cereal - Corn) (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Research Files (Dairying - Fish) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Research Files (Followup - Melons) (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Research Files (Middle Ages - Olives) (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Research Files (Pitcairn Island - Saxon Meals) (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Festive Board" - Research Files (Sheep - Wheat) (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Life and Times of the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial" - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 43A)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The Life and Times of the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial" - Typescript (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Man's Discovery of Man" - Notes and Drafts, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "The New Haven Interracial Conference of 1927" - Correspondence and Notes, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Restless Men", 1934 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Books - Nonfiction - ""Unrolling the Map" - Bibliography (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Books - Nonfiction - ""Unrolling the Map" - Motion Picture Outlines (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Promotion - (Selected Photocopies), 1933-1935 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Promotion, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Publication, 1935-1938 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Republication, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Research Notes - Africa (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Research Notes - Ancient and Classic Worlds (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Research Notes (Box 5, Folder 56)
    Antarctica After 1935 Asia Australia Explorers and Food
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Research Notes - Great Age of Adventure - Spain and Portugual (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Research Notes - Great Age of Adventure - Spain and Portugual (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Research Notes (Box 6, Folder 59)
    Heroes of American Exploration Middle Ages
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Research Notes - North Ameria After 1550 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Table of Contents (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Lectures, 1940-1972 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Outlines, undated (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "The Modern Museum: Its Purposes and Functions" - Typescript, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - Museums - Consulting, 1959-1962, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Administrative Correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Administrative Correspondence - Expenses, 1961-1964 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Administrative Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    Gulick, Luther; Gustafson, Carl; Hanks, Nancy.
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Administrative Correspondence - Publishers, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Circulation, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (Ac-Ad), 1960-1963 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (Ai-Al), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence - American Association of Museums, 1962-1965 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence - American Association of Museums - Annual Meetings, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (Am-Av), 1962 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (B), 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (C), 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (D-L), 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (M-R), 1962-1963 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Correspondence (S-Y), 1962-1965 (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Cultural Institutions and Government - Workbook (Correspondence), 1962-1965 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Cultural Institutions and Government - Workbook (Correspondence), 1962-1965 (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Cultural Institutions and Government, Europe - Workbook (Correspondence), 1963 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Dictabelt Transcriptions Covering Research (California-Massachusetts), 1962 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Dictabelt Transcriptions Covering Research (New York-Virginia), 1962 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Dictabelt Transcriptions Covering Research - Canada, England, and France, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Dictabelt Transcriptions Covering Research - Miscellaneous Topics, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - European Trip - Administrative Correspondence, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - European Trip - Correspondence - England, France, and Germany, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - European Trip - Expenses, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - European Trip - Planning, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - European Trip - Travel Schedules, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Typescript (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Unanswered Requests for Data, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums - Their Relation to Leisure-Time, Activity and Adult Education" - Typescript, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - Nature Centers (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - New York Zoological Society - "A Report for the New York Zoological Society" - Typescript, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - New York Zoological Society - "A Report for the New York Zoological Society" (Supplement to 1938 Report) - Typescript, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - New York Zoological Society - Post-World War II Plans - Notes, undated (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "A Plan for the Creation of the Hall, 'The Earth and its History' " (Report to the Academy of Natural Sciences in Philadelphia) - Typescript, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Project for Boys' Museum to be Incorporated in the University Museum, Philadelphia" - Typescript, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Business Affairs, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Correspondence, Memoranda, Notes, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 105)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - General Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 11, Folder 106)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Notes, Outlines, Summaries, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Notes, Outlines, Summaries, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Publicity, 1963-1965 (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - Studies - Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission (ORRRC) Report, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - Studies - Population - "A Report on Population" - Volume 1 - "A Short Story of Population", 1948 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Studies - Population - "A Report on Population" - Volume 2 - "Illustrations", 1948 (Box 12, Folder 112)
  - Studies - Population - "A Report on Population" - Volume 3 - "Possible Developments", 1948 (Box 12, Folder 113)
  - Studies - Volcano Research - Mt. Pel, 1931 (Box 12, Folder 114)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - "Museums and the Future" - Index Cards, 1962-1963 (Box 13, Folder 115)
  - Books - Nonfiction - "Unrolling the Map" - Scrapbook, 1934-1937 (Box 14, Folder 116)
  - Studies - Cultural Institutions - Nature Centers - Nature Centers for Young America, Inc. - "What is a Nature Center?" Brochure, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 117)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Drawing of Proposed Ocean-Going Raft - Sketch No. POGR SK-1, October 2, 1964 (Folder 1)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Box 11, Folders 107-108.
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Drawing of Proposed Ocean-Going Raft - Sketch No. POGR-3, November 12, 1964 (Folder 1, Folder 2)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Design No. C-793 - 97'-6" W.L. Three Mast Sailing Yacht - General Arrangement - Drawing No. 79304, 1967 (Folder 1, Folder 3)
    Philip L. Rhodes, Inc., Naval Architects
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Design No. C-793 - 97'-6" W.L. Three Mast Sailing Yacht - Outboard Profile - Drawing No. 79306, 1967 (Folder 1, Folder 4)
  - Studies - Gulf Stream Project - Design No. C-793 - 97'-6" W.L. Three Mast Sailing Yacht - Primary Sail Plan - Drawing No. 79303, 1967 (Folder 1, Folder 5)
- Leonard Outhwaite photographs, 1034
  Conditions Governing Access
  Photographs, slides, and other images are open for scholarly research. RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply.
  Photographs
  - Leonard Outhwaite (Box 13, Folder 177)